Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So for America's brief little
moment of imperialism at the end of the
19th century, its biggest campaign will
easily be the Spanish-American War. This
war isn't like many wars I'm sure you
know. Essentially, it started because
Cuba didn't want to be controlled by
Spain anymore, and the US was willing to
support Cuba in that regard. Propaganda
was also a big part with the growth of
yellow journalism, and the other part to
this is the sinking of the US ship the
USS Maine. Now, it's not actually truly
known what really caused the explosion
that sank this ship, but it didn't
really matter because US propaganda at
the time blamed it on Spain. As for the
war, it was actually quite quick. The US
will fight Spain, and the war will be
fought in Cuba and the Philippines, and
the US Navy will crush Spain quickly.
The decisive battle of this war will be
the Battle of Manila Bay, and a big
propaganda group that will get traction
here is the Rough Riders, which was led
by Theodore, or better known as Teddy
Roosevelt. This war will end with a
treaty that we will happily add to our
list of the many treaty Parises. This
treaty will cause Spain to give up
Puerto Rico, Guam, and the Philippines.
Puerto Rico will quietly become a US
territory, Guam will quietly become a US
naval base, and the Philippines will
become a colony of the US for $20
million. But, they will not go quietly
at all. This will trigger a
Filipino-American War, where Filipinos
led by Emilio Aguinaldo will want
independence, and the US will suppress
this nationalist movement severely. As
for Cuba, it will technically be
independent, but basically the US will
have a sh load of soldiers occupy the
country and impose a controlling Platt
Amendment. So, I'll leave the debating
up to you whether or not that's truly
independent. The other outcome of this
war is that the US will finally be
involved with Asia and open up a lot of
trade with different Asian countries
like China. On the screen now are
AP-style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.